[ORGANISER] The next person we have coming up is someone I have looked up to for quite a while.
[组织者]我们要登台的下一位演讲者， 是我很久以来一直期待的人
Whenever I [need to know] how to explain a problem in Bitcoin, it is easy to just go through his videos.
每当我[需要知道]如何解释比特币的问题时，只要浏览他的视频就答疑解惑了
He explains things so perfectly.
他的解释如此清晰易懂
He is the author of 'Mastering Bitcoin,' and spoke in front of the Canadian Senate recently.
他是《精通比特币》的作者，并且最近在加拿大参议院发表了演讲
It [received] a lot of attention. I'm sure most of you have taken a look at what he said there.
这场演讲受到了很多关注。我相信你们大多数人都看过他的演讲
It was an amazing talk. I haven't seen too many senate hearings, but it was the first time I saw them clapping,
这是一个了不起的演讲。我没见过太多参议院听证会，但这是我第一次看到他们鼓掌，
with a look on their face like, 'We just listened to something really special.'
他们脸上的表情就像是再说："我们听到了一些非常特别的东西。"
Andreas [Antonopoulos], the author of 'Mastering Bitcoin' and an amazing speaker.
Andreas [Antonopoulos]，《 精通比特币》的作者，一位了不起的演讲者
He is one person that actually has the chance to change so many minds by speaking to governments,
他是一个通过与政府对话来改变很多人想法的人
being able to talk in a way that makes things very simple, [but also] makes people think about it in a positive light.
能够以一种非常简洁的方式布道， [但也]使人们以积极的态度考虑它
Andreas, come on up! [Applause] [ANDREAS] Wow, this is amazing for a meetup.
安德里亚斯，加油！ [掌声] [安德烈亚斯]哇，这次会议太棒了
I apologise, I didn't realise this was a bring-your-own-chair event. [Laughter]
我很抱歉，我没有意识到这是一个自带椅子的活动。 [笑声]
As you see, the others each brought a chair and even color coordinated, but I forgot to bring mine.
如您所见，其他每个人都带来了一把椅子， 甚至色彩也是协调的，但我忘了带上我的
I will pace, which will drive the videographers crazy,
我会踱步，这会让摄像师们抓狂
but if you have seen my videos, you know I don't do podiums.
但是如果您看过我的视频， 你知道我不会在讲台上呆着不动
So, welcome everyone! This is really exciting, probably one of the largest meetups I have done.
所以，欢迎大家！这真的很令人兴奋， 可能是我参加过的最大的聚会之一
I think maybe the largest one was in London, but you are definitely giving them a run for their money.
我想也许最大的一个可能是在伦敦，但是 您肯定是在和他们竞争
It is really exciting to see all of this energy in Canada with cryptocurrencies.
看到所有这些在加拿大使用加密货币的能量真的很令人兴奋
A big thanks to my host, Anthony Di Iorio, who organised this [event at a] lovely space. Let's get started.
非常感谢主持人Anthony Di Iorio的组织， 这个活动在一个可爱的地方。让我们开始吧
How many of you are here for the first time, or been [recently] introduced to Bitcoin? A few people.
你们中有多少人是第一次来这里？ 或者（最近）被介绍才接触比特币？有几个人?
How many of you are pretty familiar with Bitcoin? How many of you own bitcoin? [Audience raises hands]
你们当中有多少人对比特币非常熟悉？ 你们有多少人拥有比特币？ [观众举手]
How many of you are coding with Bitcoin? Alright, fantastic.
你们当中有多少人参与比特币相关的开发？ 好吧，太好了
I want to talk about splitting hairs and the five stages of grief. [Laughter]
我想谈谈吹毛求疵和接受不幸的五个阶段。 [笑声]
I know you thought I was coming here to talk about Bitcoin;
我知道你以为我是来这里谈论比特币的；
I want to talk about Bitcoin from the public perception.
我想从公众的角度谈谈比特币
Three years ago, I would go places and tell people about Bitcoin. They had never heard of it.
三年前，我在很多地方发表演讲， 人们从未听说过比特币
They didn't know what I was talking about.
他们不知道我在说什么
I wouldn't ask people "have you heard of Bitcoin?" because that was a silly question to ask.
我不会问别人“你听说过比特币吗？” 因为那是一个愚蠢的问题
I would say, "Let me tell you about something exciting." A year later, people started hearing about Bitcoin.
我会说：“让我告诉您一些令人兴奋的事情。”一年后，人们才开始听说比特币
If I was in a technology-heavy environment -- basically, if I was surrounded by geeks --
如果我处在一个以技术为主的环境中---基本上，如果我被极客们包围着-
I would ask, "Have you heard of Bitcoin?"
我会问：“您听说过比特币吗？”
Gradually it started getting to the point where I could ask that question of, say, a taxi driver.
逐渐地，我可以问一个出租车司机类似的问题
Get into a taxi... "Have you heard of Bitcoin?"
乘坐出租车的时候……“您听说过比特币吗？”
There was this gradual transition [to] mainstream awareness and people start hearing about it.
这是一个逐渐过渡到主流意识的过程， 人们开始慢慢听说
Of course, what they're hearing is not:
当然，他们听到的可不是：
"it is one of the most amazing decentralized consensus networks and payment systems ever."
“这是最令人惊讶的去中心化共识网络和支付系统项目之一。”
What they hear about is: "DRUGS ON THE INTERNET!" [Laughter] "I was at a conference talking about bitcoin,"
他们听到的是：“互联网上的毒品！” [笑声]“我当时正在开会谈论比特币，”
you say to the average person the street.
你对街上的普通人说这些
They will look at you and take a very subtle but firm step away, just in case you throw cocaine at them. [Laughter]
他们会看着你，迈出非常微妙而坚定的一步 然后离开，以防万一你向他们扔毒品卡因。 [笑声]
The mainstream awareness right now is, we are all a bunch of degenerates, porn addicts,
现在的主流意识是 我们都是一群堕落的色情迷，
drug users, potentially terrorists, though they're not sure. It depends. Some of us, certainly.
吸毒者，可能是恐怖分子，尽管他们不确定。当然，这取决于具体情况和我们中的某些人的为人
Yeah, in this room! This is the mainstream perception.
是的，在这个房间里！这是主流看法
This is the first stage: denial. Denial happens with all innovative technologies.
这是第一阶段：拒绝。 所有创新技术都会遭到拒绝
It is that desire to dismiss change, especially if that change is strange and scary.
这是一种放弃变革的愿望， 尤其是如果这种变化是奇怪和可怕的
We were talking about banks recently, and the media. We are seeing that they've moved from denial to anger.
我们最近谈到了银行和媒体 我们看到他们已经从否认变成愤怒
Angry about the terrible things you can do, because Bitcoin is now all about "funding ISIS."
对您做的可怕事情感到生气， 因为比特币现在全都与“为ISIS筹集资金”有关
[Laughter] Who here has contributed to ISIS recently?
[大笑]最近，谁为ISIS做出了贡献？
Sorry, I raised my hand there. I pay taxes in the United States; I don't know if you have noticed,
抱歉，我刚才举手了。我在美国纳税; 我不知道你是否注意到了
but ISIS is driving M1 Abrams tanks and Humvees with the American flags hastily sprayed off.
但ISIS正在驾驶的M1艾布拉姆斯坦克和悍马，上面仓促的喷上了美国国旗
So, strictly speaking, yes: I have funded ISIS through the U.S. Department of Defense, in U.S. dollars,
因此，严格来说，是的：我通过美国国防部资助了ISIS，用的是美元
by leaving behind a lot of nice equipment, pallets of U.S. dollars, and things like that.
通过留下很多好的装备， 带着美元标识的托盘之类的东西
When I fill up my car [with gas], that money goes to Saudi Arabia; I fund ISIS that way too, oops!
当我给汽车加油时，钱就流到沙特阿拉伯；我也以这种方式资助ISIS，哎呀！
But I'll tell you this: I have never funded ISIS in bitcoin, so let's keep that straight. [Laughter]
但我会告诉你：我从未使用比特币资助ISIS，这可是大实话。 [笑声]
That's the kind of question that comes up, right? We have gone from denial to anger.
这就是目前出现的问题，对吧？ 我们已经从否认变成愤怒
Now it is not just "we don't want to hear about this Bitcoin thing,"
现在不只是“我们不想听到有关比特币的事情，”
because it's strange and possibly young people are interested in it. [Laughter]
因为它很奇怪，可能只有黄毛小儿才对此感兴趣。[笑声]
Now it's scary! We need to emphasise the scariness. You don't speak about Bitcoin in polite company.
现在太可怕了！我们需要强调它的可怕之处。不要在正式的场合谈论比特币
"Have you heard about Bit-?" "Oh no, I [will not become] involved in that kind of stuff!" [Laughter]
“您听说过Bit-吗？” “哦，不，我[不会]参与这种事情！” [笑声]
That's the second stage of grief: anger. Now we move into the third stage of grief.
那是接受不幸的第二阶段：愤怒。 现在我们进入接受不幸的第三阶段
This is really exciting, because this is where things get really silly and fun.
这真的很令人兴奋，因为这个时候事情变得愚蠢而有趣
Bargaining. You start off with "Bitcoin is irrelevant." When Bitcoin refuses to die for three years,
讨价还价。您从“比特币无关紧要”开始。 比特币顽强生存了三年
so you can't say it is irrelevant anymore.
所以你不能说它不再重要了
It is worth $10 billion, it is tradeable over the internet, people [become] excited about it,
它价值100亿美元，可以通过互联网交易，人们对此感到兴奋，
and [launch] start-ups with $500 million in investment.
会[启动]初创企业，投资额达5亿美元
That doesn't sound irrelevant anymore.
听起来不再无关紧要了
You drop that storyline and go to anger, where it is not "irrelevant" but "dangerous."
你放弃故事情节，走向愤怒， 不是“无关紧要”的，而是“危险”的
Now we move into bargaining. The new line is: "Well, blockchain technology is really promising."
现在我们开始讨价还价。新的说法是： “嗯，区块链技术确实很有前途。”
"But bitcoin the currency is just weird and volatile, you don't want to touch that." We're splitting hairs.
“但是比特币的货币只是奇怪而波动的， 你不会想碰它的。”我们开始吹毛求疵
This is the third stage of grief: bargaining.
这是接受不幸的第三阶段：讨价还价
This is becoming the meme of 2015.
这正成为2015年的热门话题
A lot of companies are trying to do this triangulation, trying to split hairs,
许多公司正在尝试做这种三角剖分，试图分分析细枝末节，
trying to say, "We will take the blockchain but you can leave that bitcoin stuff behind."
试图说：“我们将采用区块链 但您需要将比特币相关的东西抛在脑后。”
"Have you started a Bitcoin research group?" "Oh no, we don't do that stuff."
“您成立比特币研究小组了吗？” “哦，不，我们不那样做。”
"We have a blockchain research group at our bank, studying  blockchain technology."
“我们的银行，正在研究区块链技术。”
This is really hilarious. The first thing it reveals is, they don't really understand Bitcoin.
这真是好笑。它揭示的第一件事是， 他们并不真正了解比特币
You can't just cleave off the 'blockchain technology' and say, "This is revolutionary!"
你不能只是把'区块链技术”拿出来， 然后说：“这是革命性的！”
Because it is not. 'Blockchain' on its own, is not revolutionary. What do I mean by that?
因为这是不对的。单独的“区块链”，不是革命性的。这是什么意思呢？
Some of you are looking at me funny. Why am I saying the blockchain is not revolutionary?
你们有些人看着我很好笑， 为什么我说区块链不是革命性的？
Because the blockchain is a ledger. How old are ledgers? Thousands of years old.
因为区块链是一个分类帐本。 分类帐的历史有多久了？几千年了
In fact, the very first writing that we discovered around the world -- on tablets, stone, papyrus -- are ledgers.
实际上，我们在世界各地发现的最早的文字---平板电脑，石头，纸莎草纸上----都是分类帐本
If you have a page of papyrus, the very first page ever created, what do you write on it?
如果您有一页纸莎草纸，那么在第一页上面，您会在上面写什么？
You write how many goats your neighbour owes you, or how many vats of wine you sold to someone.
你写下邻居欠你多少山羊， 或您卖给某人的葡萄酒桶数
And that is a ledger. There is nothing revolutionary about [ledger] technology.
那是一个分类帐。 [分类帐]技术没有什么革命性
If you summed up all the vats of wine on the first page of papyrus,
如果你把所有的酒的数目都写到纸莎草纸第一页上
and then copied that number to the top of the second page of papyrus,
然后将这个数字复制到纸莎草纸第二页的顶部，
you are linking together these "blocks" of transactions.
您将这些“交易”链接在一起
Well, that is a blockchain. It is not really interesting technology. It has been around for ages.
好吧，那是一个区块链。这不是很有趣的技术。它已经存在了很长时间
What is really interesting is a decentralized blockchain. That is fascinating. A decentralized blockchain,
真正有趣的是去中心化的区块链。 真是令人着迷。去中心化的区块链
with no central authority, no counter-party responsible for recording information.
没有中央权力，没有负责记录信息的监督方
That is astonishingly disruptive and a revolutionary technology. That [would] change so many industries.
这是惊人的破坏性和革命性的技术。 这将改变许多行业
But that is not what they are researching in the 'blockchain research department' of a big bank.
但这不是他们在一家大银行的``区块链研究部门''所研究的
They are researching is ledgers and trying to say, "We like this blockchain idea, but can we do it...
他们正在研究分类帐，并试图瞎扯： “我们喜欢这个区块链的主意，但是我们能稍微改一下吗……
without any mining, decentralization, open access protocols, anarchic chaos, ['be your own bank'] crap?"
没有任何采矿，权力下放，开放访问协议，无政府状态的混乱，['成为自己的银行']废话？”
"Can we just get a blockchain more like Visa?" [Laughter] Bargaining, the third stage of grief.
“我们能得到像Visa那样的区块链吗？” [笑声]讨价还价，接受不幸的第三阶段
What is this grief about?
这是为什么？
One of the [most] entrenched, monopolistic, exploitative industries that exists in the world doesn't like disruption.
世界上最根深蒂固的，垄断性的，剥削性的的行业之一不喜欢颠覆
In banking, disruption cuts into the profit margin.
在银行业，业务中断会削减利润率
Bitcoin is disruptive; Bitcoin is not just a bit disruptive.
比特币是破坏性的；比特币不只是有点破坏性
Bitcoin [doesn't say], "Hey, maybe we [will compete with the other] payment networks."
比特币[不会说]，“嘿，也许我们[会与其他]付款网络竞争。”
Bitcoin isn't like PayPal, which [bankers] co-opted and gradually morphed into a baby Visa. [Laughter]
比特币不像[银行]选择的PayPal， 后者逐渐演变成一种Visa宝宝。 [笑声]
Bitcoin refuses to be co-opted in that way, because it has certain pesky characteristics:
比特币拒绝以这种方式被吸收， 因为它具有某些烦人的特征：
decentralization, open access, [open-source] protocols...
去中心化，开放访问，[开放源代码]协议...
you know, all the stuff they are trying to cut off and remove so they can turn it into [another] baby Visa.
你知道，他们试图切断和删除一切，以便他们可以将其转换为[另一个]Visa宝宝
Bitcoin refuses to go away, despite all the smears, bad language, and [accusations] of funding ISIS and drugs.
比特币拒绝投降，尽管他被抹黑，被说脏话，被指控资助ISIS和毒品
Bitcoin is extremely disruptive in a way we haven't yet realized.
比特币在某种程度上极具破坏性， 我们还没有意识到这一点
Even people who are [interested in] Bitcoin don't really understand what is going on here.
甚至对[比特币]感兴趣的人也没有真正了解这里发生了什么
Let's look back a few years. Do you remember the dawn of MP3?
让我们回顾前几年。 您还记得MP3的起源吗
I actually heard about MP3 two years before Napster came out, when it was [still] an obscure [algorithm]...
事实上，早在Napster出现的两年前，我就听说过MP3，当时它[仍然]是一个晦涩的[算法] ...
from the Fraunhofer Institute in Germany.
来自德国弗劳恩霍夫研究所
They designed this lossy compression algorithm that was [very] effective, but I didn't get it.
他们设计了这种有损压缩算法 它（非常）有效，但是我没有理解它
I didn't see that [it would] do anything [interesting]. Gradually, it started eating away at the music industry.
我没看到它[会]做任何[有趣的事情]。 逐渐地，它开始蚕食音乐产业
With the invention of Napster, it turned every computer into a desktop music station.
随着Napster的发明， 它把每台电脑都变成了一个桌面音乐工作站
Suddenly, the music industry was threatened.
突然之间，音乐产业受到了威胁
They fought Napster, Napster turned into Kazaa, Kazaa turned into Limewire; they fought Limewire,
他们与Napster战斗，Napster变成了Kazaa，Kazaa变成了Limewire；他们与Limewire战斗，
Limewire turned into Gnutella; they fought Gnutella and got BitTorrent.
Limewire变成了Gnutella； 他们与Gnutella战斗，最终出现了BitTorrent
Then they gave up. They couldn't fight anymore, because it was decentralized.
然后他们放弃了。他们没有了战斗对象 ，因为它是去中心化的
Bitcoin started that way, where BitTorrent left off, in the "you can't squash this" mode.
比特币就是这样开始的，BitTorrent 就是这样开始的，他们的模式类似，都是"你没办法打压这个"的模式
MP3 destabilized the music industry. [How much is] the music industry [worth], $100 billion?
MP3破坏了音乐产业的稳定。 音乐产业[市值]有多少，价值1,000亿美元吗？
Peanuts. Apple swallowed it in a couple of years.
苹果在几年内就吞下了它
When Bitcoin starts disrupting the banking industry, it [will] apply something we call "disintermediation."
当比特币开始扰乱银行业时， 它会应用我们称为“去中介化”的东西
Disintermediation is when an industry you painstakingly built over a hundred years, becomes obsolete overnight.
去中介化的意思是，您辛勤工作的行业建造了一百多年，一夜之间过时了
Disintermediation is when you and I want to do something, and someone [offers a service]...
去中介化是您和我想要做生意，某人[提供服务] ...
to help us do that thing, but we don't need them anymore.
帮助我们做那件事，但是我们不再需要它们了
When you [have] disintermediation in the music industry, it cuts record labels out of the sweet deals,
当您在音乐界去中介化时， 它削减了唱片公司的甜蜜交易
[but] it allows customers to work directly with artists, and the record companies do not like that.
[但是]它允许客户直接与艺术家合作， 唱片公司不喜欢这样
But that is still a little industry [in comparison].
但[相比之下]这还是一个小行业
When we start disintermediating the financial services industry,
特别是我们开始在金融服务业去中介化
entire multi-billion dollar layers will evaporate overnight.
整个数十亿美元的业务将在一夜之间蒸发
Bitcoin is incredibly disruptive because of all those little things they pretend are not really important.
比特币具有令人难以致信的破坏性， 仅仅因为所有这些他们假装不重要的小特性
What comes after bargaining? Depression. [Laughter]
讨价还价后会发生什么？萧条。 [笑声]
It is a great word, because financial depression already happened in 2008. I think we are about to see a replay.
这是一个好词，因为金融萧条已经在2008年发生过了。我认为我们将看到重播
The financial industry [will not be ready for] this fight.
金融业[没有为]这场斗争做好准备
They are going in leveraged up to their eyeballs, with the worst reputation in two hundred years.
他们正竭尽全力，他们正处在200年中声誉最差的时期
Everyone under 18 years old thinks that banks are the worst thing ever invented,
18岁以下的每个人都认为银行是有史以来最糟糕的发明，
and are responsible for stealing their jobs -- because they did.
他们要为偷走了他们的工作负责---因为他们就是这样做的
When you have an entire generation that hates you, exactly the generation that [will] adopt this technology,
当有一整代的人讨厌你时， 他们[将]采用这项技术
and you go into this fight leveraged up to your eyeballs, depression sets in pretty quickly.
然后你进入这场战斗 萧条很快就会发生
Some of the banks [will] be smarter and skip right over to acceptance.
一些银行[将]变得更聪明， 直接跳过去接受它
We saw this with the Internet. At first, everyone was banding together.
我们通过互联网看到了这一点。 起初，每个人都团结在一起
The phone companies said, "We will not let this thing eat our long-distance market!" [Laughter]
电话公司说：“我们不会让这个东西吞噬我们的长途电话市场！” [笑声]
I remember when I used to call home to Greece from my college in London.
我记得我以前从伦敦的大学打电话给希腊的家的时候
To [have] a ten-minute conversation, I would literally [need] a stack of coins...
我真的需要一堆硬币，来进行十分钟的对话..
and feed them into the meter every ten seconds or so.
并每隔十秒左右将它们投入计价器
My entire family would line up on the other end of the call and parade themselves in front of the telephone:
我的整个家庭将在另一端排队 在电话前介绍自己:
"Hello Andreas, this is Uncle John. How are you?" "Very well, thank you." "Yes, here's your Auntie Maria."
“你好安德里亚斯，这是约翰叔叔。你好吗？” “很好，谢谢。” “是的，这是你的玛丽亚姨妈。”
"Oh, hello Maria..." and so on, fifteen seconds per person, carefully allocated, moving [down] the line.
“哦，玛丽亚，你好……”，以此类推，每人十五秒， 仔细分配，向下移动
Keep the line moving, people! Because I just spent £8 to make a fifteen minute phone call.
继续排队，各位！因为我刚刚花了8英镑打了15分钟的电话
When I testified in front of the Australian Senate, they said,
当我在澳大利亚参议院作证时，他们说
"This [was] really difficult to arrange [but] we thank you for speaking to us from such a great distance today."
“这[安排]确实很难[但是]我们感谢您 今天从这么远的地方和我们说话。”
My last words to the Australian Senate were:
我对澳大利亚参议院的最后一句话是：
"Just remember, phone companies didn't write the rules for the internet, and that is why I could do this today."
“请记住，电话公司并没有为互联网制定规则，这就是为什么我今天可以做到这一点。”
Because trust me, if phone companies had written the rules for the Internet,
因为相信我，如果电话公司制定了互联网规则，
there would be a little slot inside of my Mac Air and I would need to feed quarters into it...
我的Mac Air内部会有一个小插槽 而且我需要在其中塞进硬币…
[Laughter] every ten seconds during the Skype calls I make, just to preserve the long-distance market.
[笑声]当我在Skype通话的时候，每十秒钟就得投个币，只是为了保护长途电话市场
When that was happening, eventually some companies decided they [would] break ranks,
当这种情况发生时，最终一些公司决定他们[将]打破常规，
and turn themselves into internet service providers.
把自己变成互联网服务提供商
This [will] be a lot harder to do in the banking industry. Bitcoin is a very difficult and bitter pill to swallow.
要在银行业中做到这一点，[将]难得多， 比特币是一种很难吞咽的苦药
The idea that banks [will] simply 'do a bit of blockchain' and fight this disruption, is ludicrous on its face.
银行[将]简单地“使用一点区块链技术”的主意，并与这种颠覆作斗争，这是荒谬的
'Doing a bit of blockchain' doesn't serve the other six billion [unbanked].
'来一点区块链技术'不会服务其他60亿[没有银行帐户]的人
'Doing a bit of blockchain' doesn't unleash the torrent of innovation that comes with open-access protocols.
'来一点区块链技术'不会释放访问协议带来的创新的洪流
Most importantly, 'a bit of blockchain' with a centralized counter-party in the middle of every transaction...
最重要的是，“一点点的区块链技术”将每笔交易中带有集中式监管的交易方...
takes us right back to the world we live in today, where control over money is control over freedom...
带我们回到当今生活的世界， 对货币的控制就是对自由的控制...
and most of the world lives as slaves.
世界上大部分地区，人们都过着奴隶的生活
Bitcoin [will] change that. Thank you. [Applause]
比特币将改变这种状况。谢谢。 [掌声]